Guide to the Annette Dyar Letters 1945-1947 MS 3220
New-York Historical Society
Annette Dyar letters
1945-1947
New-York Historical Society
Sherman, Annette Dyar, 1919-2020
MS 3220
0.209 Linear feet in 1 half document box.
Approximately 35 letters written by Annette Dyar, a librarian at the New York Public Library's St. Agnes Branch, back home to her family in Eureka, Illinois. The letters chronicle her library work, social activities, romantic life, and eventual marriage.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Catherine McEwen, daughter of the author, Annette Dyar Sherman, 2022.
Arrangement
The letters are filed chronologically, followed by the typed transcription.
Biographical / Historical
Annette Dyar, a native of Eureka, Illinois, was born on October 23, 1919 to Wilmer Merit and Emma Grace (Fish) Dyar. Her father served as assistant superintendent of the Woodford County Schools. Her mother was a homemaker. Annette obtained a bachelor's degree from Eureka College in 1941, and a degree in library science from the University of Illinois in 1942. After graduate school she was employed as a cryptanalytic aide by the U.S. Army Signal Corps during World War II; even late in life she refused to reveal details of her classified war work. In 1946 she moved to Manhattan, where she began working as a librarian in the New York Public Library system. During the period covered by the present collection, she worked at NYPL's St. Agnes Branch on the Upper West Side. Employed by NYPL until 1970, she next worked for the Miami-Dade Public Library System until 1986. She retired to Marietta, Georgia, in 1991, and returned to her birthplace in 2002. Annette Dyar married fellow librarian William James Elliott in New York in 1947. She married her second husband, Forman Sherman, in 1995. Annette Dyar Sherman died in Eureka, age 100, on August 30, 2020.
For further information, see "Annette Sherman Chronicles Life" (Woodford Chronicle, June 19, 2013); "At 98, Eureka native still secretive about World War II code breaking" (Journal Star, November 11, 2017); "Eureka native turns 100, talks about her life during World War II" (Courier Newspapers, November 21, 2019); and "Annette Sherman, October 23, 1919 – August 30, 2020" (obituary, Argo-Ruestman-Harris Funeral Home).
Related Materials
Digitized, searchable versions of most of the letters in this collection, along with others, are hosted online via CARLI (Consortium of Academic and Research Libraries in Illinois), under the title "The WWII Letters of Annette Dyar Sherman (Eureka College)" at collections.carli.illinois.edu/digital/collection/erk_wwii.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of approximately 35 letters written between 1945 and 1947 by Annette Dyar to her family at home in Eureka, Illinois (810 South Main Street). During this time, Annette's father, Wilmer Merit Dyar (1884–1974), was assistant superintendent of the Woodford County Schools. Her mother, Emma Grace (Fish) Dyar (1886–1959), was a homemaker. Annette's younger brothers, Paul Edwin Dyar (1922–2004) and John Richard "Jack" Dyar (1924–1991), had just completed their wartime service with the U.S. Army Air Corps and U.S. Army Special Services Division. An older brother, Wilmer Eugene "Gene" Dyar (1916–1942), a bombardier with the Army Air Corps, was shot down and reported missing in action in 1942.
Immediately after her employment as a cryptanalytic aide with the U.S. Army Signal Corps ended, Annette moved from Washington, D.C. to New York City in early 1946. A graduate of the University of Illinois with a degree in library science, she found work at the St. Agnes Branch of the New York Public Library. Her letters chronicle her busy activities there, dinners with friends, church services she attended, excursions back to Washington, and her moves from one Manhattan apartment to the next. During this period (1945–1947) she lived at four addresses: 138 East 38th Street (Tatham House, Y.W.C.A.); 126 Riverside Drive; 40 Sherman Avenue (where she roomed with a Mrs. Hoskins or Haskins); and 147 East 60th Street. The last address she would soon share with her first husband, fellow librarian William James "Bill" Elliott, who appears as one of several young men Annette dated towards the end of the series, and whom she married on January 31, 1947.
Letters (correspondence); Menus.; Postcards.; Programs (documents); Librarians -- Correspondence.; Librarians -- United States.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; New York Public Library
- Annette Dyar letters, 1945-1947
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1945 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    One empty envelope postmarked November 7, 1945 with the return address of 1011 17th St. N.W., Washington, D.C., and one letter dated November 12, 1945, missing its envelope and return address, but also likely written from Washington.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Three letters written from Tatham House, Y.W.C.A., 138 East 38th Street, January 11, 13, and [20], 1946; one written from 126 Riverside Drive, January 24, 1946; and one written from 40 Sherman Avenue, January 30, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Three letters and one postcard written from 40 Sherman Avenue, February 3, 13, and 28, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Two letters written from 40 Sherman Avenue, March 14 and 21, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    One letter written from 40 Sherman Avenue, April 21, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Four letters written from 40 Sherman Avenue, May 1, 14, 21, and 29, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Four letters written from 40 Sherman Avenue, June 11, [21], 22, and 28, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Two letters written from 40 Sherman Avenue, July 9 and 21, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Two letters written from 40 Sherman Avenue, August 3 and 8, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    One letter written from 40 Sherman Avenue, September 16, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    One letter written from 40 Sherman Avenue, October 8, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Three letters written from 147 East 60th Street, November 11, 17, and 25, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1946 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Two letters written from 147 East 60th Street, December 10 and 22, 1946.
  - Annette Dyar letters, 1947 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    Two letters written from 147 East 60th Street, January 13 and 15, 1947.
  - "Letters from New York City: Annette Dyar, 1945–1947", [2010] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    Spiral bound, typed and illustrated transcription of the letters, compiled by Catherine Elliott McEwen (daughter of the author), and edited by Annette Dyar Sherman and Abigail McEwen, 2010.